<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons most humbly offer'd by the po[or] tradesmen, for passing the salt-petre bill</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B43793</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">489265140</idno>
  <idno type="VID">208694</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240872042</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 489265140</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 489265140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R570A</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B43793)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 208694)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2956:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons most humbly offer'd by the po[or] tradesmen, for passing the salt-petre bill</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Saltpeter industry --  Taxation --  Law and legislation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Tariff --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="genre_form">Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:208694:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:208694:2"/>
            <head>REASONS most humbly offer'd by the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Tradesmen, for Passing the <hi>Salt-petre</hi> Bill.</head>
            <p>WHereas in a printed Paper, against passing the said Bill, delivered at this most Honourable House, it is most falsely (and self-interested<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) asserted, by some Engroslers of that small quantity of <hi>Salt petre</hi> now in <hi>England,</hi> That the Pretences of the poor Tradesmen, who sollicite the passing the said Bill, are frivolous and inconsiderable, the said Engrossers well knowing, if the <hi>East-India</hi> Company's <hi>Salt-petre</hi> should arive safe, the same must be kept for Their Majesties use, and the poor Tradesmen must be forced to buy of them at their extravagant Prizes; which the passing the said Bill will prevent.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Refiners, Glass-makers,</hi> and <hi>Dyers,</hi> do attend, and are ready to make out, to the full satisfaction of this most Honourable House,</p>
            <p>That without <hi>Salt-petre,</hi> the said Trades cannot be carried on.</p>
            <p>That in these Trades, upwards of 300 Tons is yearly expended.</p>
            <p>That if <hi>Salt-petre</hi> bears the intollerable high Price it now doth and hath done, for a long time past, the said Tradesmen and their Families must in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably be ruined.</p>
            <p>For by the dearness of <hi>Salt-petre</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> Scarlet and <hi>Bow</hi> Dyers cannot Dye so cheap as the <hi>Dutch,</hi> therefore Merchants send Cloths to <hi>Holland</hi> to be Dyed. And they also have a great Advantage of us, by Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own Cloths cheap for the <hi>Turkey</hi> Trade, to the prejudice of the Woollen Manufacture of this Nation.</p>
            <p>For the same Reason the <hi>Refiners</hi> are forced to send their Silver to <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be separated.</p>
            <p>And for the like Reason the <hi>Glass-makers</hi> cannot make Glass to sell at Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Rates, as formerly, by which the Nation suffers in general.</p>
            <p>By these Advantages the <hi>Dutch</hi> are enrich'd, and the poor Tradesmen impoverish'd. As also the Gunpowder-makers, Merchants, and Masters of Ships; for when <hi>Salt-petre</hi> was cheap in <hi>England,</hi> there was upwards of 900 Tuns used yearly, for Gunpowder to Export, besides what Their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties and the Tradesmen expended.</p>
            <p>But by reason of the dearness of <hi>Salt-petre</hi> now in <hi>England,</hi> we lose the benefit of manufacturing so much <hi>Salt-petre</hi> yearly, which will make 1200 Tons of Gunpowder, and also lose the Exporting of the said 1200 Tons of Gunpowder. And <hi>Ireland,</hi> and our Plantations in the <hi>West Indies,</hi> cannot be supplyed by us, when Gunpouder is above 5 <hi>l.</hi> the Barrel; for by Law it cannot be then Exported. And at the Price <hi>Salt-petre</hi> now bears, and hath done for a long time past, Gunpouder cannot be made under 6 <hi>l.</hi> the Barrel; but the <hi>Dutch</hi> find ways to supply them.</p>
            <p>And whereas the <hi>East-India</hi> Company, in their Petition to this most Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable House, desire, if leave be given to Import <hi>Salt-petre,</hi> it may be to them only. If so, they may choose if they will Import any or no: And so do, as has been done, make no publick Sale for three or four Years together, but impose upon the Tradesmen, by Selling by private Contracts.</p>
            <p>And it is not yet certain, whether they shall continue a Company or no.</p>
            <p>Their Case is most humbly recommended to the Compassion of this most Honourable House.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="docket_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:208694:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>REASONS</hi> Most humbly offer'd by the poor Tradesmen, For passing the Salt-petre Bill.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>